Guide to the Alexander Proctor papers, 1837-1895
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library Duke University Durham, N.C., USA
Alexander Proctor papers 1837-1895
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University
Proctor, Alexander, 1814-1865
.1 Linear Feet 36 Items
African American family originally from Virginia and North Carolina.
Legal papers and correspondence relating to the Alexander Proctor family, tracing their history beginning as freedmen in Virginia and North Carolina, their 1840s resettlement in Warren County, Ohio, their emigration to Haiti in 1861 as part of the Redpath movement, and their eventual return to Kalamazoo, Michigan in 1866. The correspondence dates principally from the 1870s, is chiefly written by A.W. Proctor, one of Alexander Proctor's sons, and S.S. Hutchins, friend of Proctor's son, Isaac, and relates to family affairs, business, and other matters. S.S. Hutchins is identified in the Gould's St. Louis Directory (1874), 449, as Chief Clerk in the U.S. Army Engineer's Office. One letter from a friend to a family member mentions seeing Frederick Douglass at Wilberforce College in 1893. The legal records document the free status of the Proctors, various labor agreements, and migration papers, and include receipts and letters of introduction.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. There may be a 48-hour delay in obtaining these materials.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Alexander Proctor papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a purchase in 1978.
Biographical Note
The Proctors were a free African American family from the South, who left Virginia in the early 1840s, lived in Warren County, Ohio, moved to Canada in 1860, and emigrated to Haiti in 1861. Alexander Proctor (1814-1865), a Baptist minister, died there, and his family, headed by wife Margaret Chaven Proctor (1814-?), returned to the U.S. and settled in Kalamazoo, Michigan with one of her sons.
Collection Overview
One-folder collection of 19th century legal papers and correspondence concerning the migratory movements, legal status, life situations, and relationships of members of a free African American family. The correspondence dates principally from the 1870s, is chiefly written by A.W. Proctor, one of Alexander Proctor's sons, and S.S. Hutchins, friend of Proctor's son, Isaac, and relates to family affairs, business, and other matters. S.S. Hutchins is identified in the Gould's St. Louis Directory (1874), 449, as Chief Clerk in the U.S. Army Engineer's Office. One letter from a friend to a family member mentions seeing Frederick Douglass at Wilberforce College in 1893.
The legal records document the free status of the Proctors, various labor agreements, and migration papers, and include receipts and letters of introduction. Official documents from Haiti are written in French and include an 1865 order permitting the burial of Proctor at St. Marc, Haiti. In terms of the context relating to the family's emigration to Haiti, many people that emigrated by way of the Redpath Agency to Haiti, as was the case for the Proctors, either died or were untraceable by 1864, and few managed to return to the U.S.
Subject Headings
These are searchable subject entries for this collection. Performing a search on these subjects in the Duke University Libraries online catalog will bring up other related research materials.
Proctor, Alexander, 1814-1865
Proctor, Margaret
Proctor family
Douglass, Frederick, 1818-1895
African Americans -- Migrations -- History -- 19th century
African Americans -- North Carolina
African Americans -- Michigan
African Americans -- Ohio
African Americans -- Haiti
African American families
Back to Africa movement
Freedmen -- North Carolina
Freedmen -- Virginia -- History -- 19th century
Indentured servants -- United States
Missionaries -- Haiti
Redpath movement
Haiti -- Emigration and immigration
Michigan -- Emigration and immigration
Ohio -- Emigration and immigration
Saint-Marc (Haiti) -- Emigration and immigration
Warren County (Ohio) -- Emigration and immigration
Contents of Collection
- Legal Papers, 1837-1866, (21 items)
  Series begins with a brief descriptive sketch of the Proctors and the nature of this collection. The legal papers include documents demonstrating that Alexander and Margaret Proctor were free persons in Virginia and North Carolina. The papers also document the travels and various life events of the Proctor family up through Margaret Proctor's permission to return to the U.S. after the death of her husband Alexander Proctor in St. Marc, Haiti, in 1865.
  - Brief descriptive sketch of the Proctors and the contents and historical context of the collection, undated (Folder 1)
  - Articles of agreement for Thomas Proctor, a free Negro to bind himself in service for 5 years to G. H. Crosman, Capt. U.S. Army, 1837 July 18 (Folder 1)
  - Recommendation for hiring for work with boats for Alexander Proctor, a free man from J. M. Jeffress, 1839 Dec. 4 (Folder 1)
  - Official statement from Clerks Office of Charlotte Co., Va. that Margaret Proctor was born to a free family in that county, 1840 Apr. 7 (Folder 1)
  - Official statement from Clerk's Office of Mecklenburg Co., Va. that Alexander Proctor was born to a free woman in Granville Co, NC, 1840 Apr. 16 (Folder 1)
  - Deposition for case pending in the Supreme Court of Mercer Co, Ohio, detailing testimony of John Anthony concerning a case between Melchen Adam Meyer and Samuel Gray over a horse, circa 1842 (Folder 1)
  - Document affirming the good citizenship and moral character of Alexander Proctor, signed by 36 members of the community in Mason, Warren Co., Ohio, 1843 Oct. 20 (Folder 1)
  - Document pertaining to land transfer to Alexander Proctor, 1845 Apr. 9 (Folder 1)
  - Charles Moore deed to Alex. Proctor, 1845 Apr. 11 (Folder 1)
  - Document verifying religious beliefs of and recommending Alexander and Margaret Proctor to other churches, from Regular A. S. Baptist Church of Beaver Creek, Ohio, 1852 Dec. 18 (Folder 1)
  - Affirmation concerning the ordination of Alexander Proctor to the work of the Gospel ministering by the laying on of hands, prepared by the First Baptist Church of Little River at Windsor Ontario Canada West, Apr. 27, no year (Folder 1)
  - Receipt for payment from Alexander Proctor to Treasurer's Office of Miami University, 1855 Nov. 1 (Folder 1)
  - Agreement for Alexander Proctor to rent land belonging to Leon St. Louis, 1860 Feb. 4 (Folder 1)
  - Register entitled Emigration to Hayti, from the Township of Sandwich County of Essex Canada West, 1861, which lists Alexander and Margaret Proctor, and two of their sons, William (21) and Samuel (14), among several others planning to emigrate. (Folder 1)
  - Emigrant's copy of Haytian Bureau of Emigration Agreement with Alexander Proctor and family, arranged by James Redpath of Boston, Gen. Agent of Emigration, noting the family received 3 tickets for passage to Haiti, 1861 June 15. (Folder 1)
  - Letter of introduction of The Reverend Alexander Proctor, written by B. F. Whidden, United States' Commissioner, Consul General, Haiti, 1864 Mar. 12 (Folder 1)
  - Document from the Bureau L'Etat Civil in Haiti, in French, concerning Elder Alexander Proctor, 1865 May 30 (Folder 1)
  - Official government document from Republic of Haiti for Margaret Proctor, in French, 1865 July 3 (Folder 1)
  - Note concerning Margaret Proctor, in French, 1865 Nov. 16 (Folder 1)
  - Official notice from Consulate of the United States of America, Camille Lynch, that Margaret Proctor should be granted passage and aid into the U.S., 1866 Apr. 12 (Folder 1)
  - Prayer or invocation, handwritten, author unknown, undated (Folder 1)
- Correspondence, 1865-1895, (15 items)
  Includes personal and business correspondence between family members and friends of the Proctor family from 1865 to 1893. Many of the letters are written by A.W. Proctor, one of Alexander Proctor's sons, and S.S. Hutchins, friend of Proctor's son, Isaac.
  - Letter, Jan. 3, 1865, from Elizabeth Jackson, Oxford, Ohio, to Nephew (Folder 1)
  - Letter, May 11, 1866, from A.W. Proctor, Kalamazoo, Mich., to Mother (Margaret Proctor) (Folder 1)
    A.W. Proctor says he is thankful to hear that she is back in the U.S. and urges her to come live with him.
  - Letter, Aug. 19, 1870, from A.W. Proctor, Kalamazoo, Mich., to Brother (Folder 1)
  - Letter, July 7, 1873, from S.S. Hutchins, St. Louis, MO, to Isaac (Proctor) (Folder 1)
  - Letter, Aug. 2, 1873, from S.S. Hutchins, St. Louis, MO, to Isaac (Proctor) (Folder 1)
  - Letter, Mar. 17, 1874, from A.W. Proctor, Kalamazoo, Mich., to Brother (Folder 1)
  - Letter, Sept. 21, 1874, from S.S. Hutchins, St. Louis, MO, to Friend (Isaac Proctor) (Folder 1)
  - Letter, Sept. 24, 1874, from A.W. Proctor, Star Landing, to Mother (Folder 1)
  - Letter, Oct. 24, 1874, from S.S. Hutchins, St. Louis, MO, to Isaac (Proctor) (Folder 1)
  - Letter, Dec. 12, 1874, from A.W. Proctor, Decatur, to Brother (Folder 1)
  - Letter, May 10, 1875, from A.W. Proctor, Decatur, to Mother (Folder 1)
  - Letter, Dec. 25, 1875, from J.C. Howland, Detroit, Mich., to S. I. Proctor (Folder 1)
  - Letter, June 25, 1877, from Chavens, Union City, to Sir (Folder 1)
  - Letter, Mar. 11, 1893, from B.A.S., Washington D.C., to Dean P. Phillips (daughter of Alexander Proctor) (Folder 1)
    Includes reference to bad weather for parade for President Cleveland's inauguration.
  - Letter, June 28, 1893, unknown author, Detroit, Mich., to Friend (Dean) (Folder 1)
    Incomplete letter with pages missing. Refers to meeting with Frederick Douglass at Wilberforce.